A Guide to the Papers of William H. Muller, Jr., 1945-2007
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of William H. Muller, Jr. 1945-2007
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-48
12 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 5' 5", 210 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by William H. Muller, Jr., in March 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. William H. Muller, Jr. was born in Dillon, South Carolina, on August 19, 1919, graduated from the McCallie School in Chattanooga, Tennessee, earned his B.S. from The Citadel in 1940, and graduated from Duke University Medical School in 1943. Muller trained under Dr. Alfred Blalock at Johns Hopkins Hospital where he did his internship and residencies in general surgery and cardiovascular surgery. From April 1946 to August 1947 he was a captain stationed overseas with the U.S. Army. He was then in private practice in Dillon for a year before returning to John Hopkins Hospital for further training. He served as an Instructor in Surgery at the Johns Hopkins Medical School for one year prior to taking the position of Assistant Professor of Surgery in 1949 at UCLA and helping to establish a new medical school with Dr. William Longmire. He served for a period of time as Chief of General Surgery and developed a cardiothoracic surgical program in the Harbor General Hospital and the St. John's Hospital because the UCLA Hospital had not yet been completed.
He was recruited to come to Charlottesville as Chair of the Department of Surgery and the S. Hurt Watts Professor in 1954. At that time the department had five faculty members. He recruited new faculty whom he helped develop and created a nationally recognized Department of Surgery. He served as Chair until 1982. Dr. Muller became Vice President for Health Affairs in 1976 and held that position until 1987 when he became Special Assistant to the President of the University. He was critical to the creation in 1980 of the Health Services Foundation, an organization that increased the money available for faculty salaries and for running the School of Medicine. He was also a driving force behind the construction of the new University of Virginia Hospital which opened in 1989.
Dr. Muller was a pioneer in the field of heart surgery. When Dr. Blalock operated on the first 'blue baby', a child with a congenital defect known as the "tetralogy of Fallot," Dr. Muller was in the room. While in Los Angeles he developed the pulmonary artery banding procedure and was able to apply it to clinical cases. He shared the honor of being one of two surgeons who performed the earliest total aortic valve replacement in 1958 and designed his own Muller valve from Teflon.
In addition to his leadership in California, at the University of Virginia and in clinical medicine, Dr. Muller was involved in many national organizations. He was a founder of the Association for Academic Surgery. He was president of the Society of University Surgeons, the Society for Vascular Surgery, the Southern Surgical Association, and the American Surgical Association. He became a member of the Board of Regents of the American College of Surgeons in 1971, was made Chairman of the Board in 1976, and was President-elect in 1978. He served as President of the College in 1979-1980. Dr. Muller served as an active member of the Executive Committee from 1974 to 1987.
In 1968 a group of his former residents created the Muller Surgical Society in his honor. He was the recipient of the Thomas Jefferson Award from the University of Virginia in 1982 and the Walter Reed Distinguished Achievement Award from the UVa Medical Alumni Association in 1997.
Married to Hildwin Clare for over 50 years and the father of three children, Dr. Muller retired in 1990. He died in Irvington, Virginia, at the age of 92, on April 19, 2012.
Scope and Content
The collection includes personal and professional correspondence. Some are family letters, most are professionally related. Included University of Virginia correspondents are John T. Ashley, Robert M. Carey, Rose M. Chioni, Kenneth Crispell, Don E. Detmer, Richard F. Edlich, Frank L. Hereford, R. Scott Jones, Norman J. Knorr, and Robert M. O'Neil. Correspondents outside of UVa include W. G. Anlyan, Willard E. Goodwin, Hiram C. Polk, Mark M. Ravitch, Jonathan E. Rhoads, Robert S. Sparkman, H. William Scott, and Richard L. Varco. Dr. Muller was a member of many organizations and some of those are represented here including the American College of Surgeons, American Surgical Association, Halsted Society, Medical Society of Virginia, Muller Surgical Society, Society of University Surgeons, Southern Society for Clinical Research, and Southern Surgical Association. There is also a 25 page recollection of his time with Dr. Alfred Blalock, a UVa Surgery Department scrapbook, photos, and slides of the construction of the 1989 hospital.
Arrangement
Boxes one through four contain personal and professional correspondence arranged alphabetically by name. Also included are news clippings about Dr. Muller. Boxes five through nine contain correspondence and documents related to Dr. Muller's professional organizations and some of his lectures, again arranged alphabetically. The end of box 9 includes photos and miscellaneous clippings. Box 10 contains documents and photos related to the 1989 hospital planning and ground-breaking. Box 11 contains pages from Dr. Muller's scrapbook which covers 1967-1972 and also an architectural drawing of the Medical Center area. Box 12 is stored in the Vault and contains slides showing the progression of the construction process of the 1989 University of Virginia Hospital.
Contents List
- Correspondence: A; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 001-001)
- Correspondence: W. G. Anlyan, Chancellor for Health Affairs, Duke University Medical Center; 1983-1989 (Box-folder 001-002)
- Correspondence: John T. Ashley, Executive Director, University of Virginia Hospitals; 1986-1989 (Box-folder 001-003)
  Includes John Ashley's curriculum vitae.
- Correspondence: B; 1992 (Box-folder 001-004)
- Correspondence: Richard H. Blank; 1986-1987 (Box-folder 001-005)
- Correspondence: Robert M. Carey; 1987-1990 (Box-folder 001-006)
  Carey was Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine.
- Correspondence: Rose M. Chioni; 1988-1989 (Box-folder 001-007)
  Chioni was Dean of the University of Virginia School of Nursing.
- Correspondence: Citadel; 1982-1988 (Box-folder 001-008)
- Correspondence: Kenneth Crispell, Acting Dean and Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine; 1956-1968 (Box-folder 001-009)
- Correspondence: D; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 001-010)
- Correspondence: Don E. Detmer, Vice President for Health Sciences; 1986-1989 (Box-folder 001-011)
  Includes correspondence about renaming of hospital buildings, hospital dedication budget, and also Don Detmer's curriculum vitae.
- Correspondence: E; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 001-012)
- Correspondence: Richard F. Edlich, Department of Plastic Surgery; 1983-1990 (Box-folder 001-013)
  Includes Richard Edlich's curriculum vitae.
- Correspondence: F; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 001-014)
- Correspondence: G; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 002-001)
  Includes letters to the Gwathmey family: Frank and Marietta, Claire, Winston, and William.
- Correspondence: Willard E. Goodwin, Professor of Urology, UCLA Medical Center; 1954-1984 (Box-folder 002-002)
  Reprinted from Science, May 18, 1956.
- Correspondence: Ha; 1979-1990 (Box-folder 002-003)
  Includes correspondence concerning C. Rollins Hanlon and John B. Hanks and Hanks' curriculum vitae.
- Correspondence: He-Hz; 1983-1990 (Box-folder 002-004)
- Correspondence: Frank L. Hereford, Jr.; 1983-1987 (Box-folder 002-005)
  Hereford was President of the University of Virginia.
- Correspondence: I; 1984-1988 (Box-folder 002-006)
- Correspondence: J; 1983-1990 (Box-folder 002-007)
- Correspondence: R. Scott Jones; 1983-1989 (Box-folder 002-008)
  Jones was Chairman of the University of Virginia Department of Surgery.
- Correspondence: K; 1973-1990 (Box-folder 002-009)
  Includes Irving L. Kron's curriculum vitae.
- Correspondence: Norman J. Knorr, Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine; 1982-1988 (Box-folder 002-010)
  Includes color photos from Knorr's (retirement?) dinner.
- Correspondence: L; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 002-011)
- Correspondence: Ma-Me; 1983-1990, AD (Box-folder 003-001)
- Correspondence: Mi-Mz; 1971-1990 (Box-folder 003-002)
  Includes letters to Muller family members. Includes letter, given by Diana Houchens, from C. Bruce Morton about his book on the Department of Surgery.
- Correspondence: McCallie School; 1983-1989 (Box-folder 003-003)
- Correspondence, articles, newspaper clippings: William H. Muller, Jr.; 1953-1979 (Box-folder 003-004)
- Correspondence, articles: William H. Muller, Jr.; 1980-1985 (Box-folder 003-005)
- Correspondence, articles, newspaper clippings: William H. Muller, Jr.; 1986-1989 (Box-folder 003-006)
- Correspondence: William H. Muller, Jr. Retirement; 1987 (Box-folder 003-007)
- Correspondence: N; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 004-001)
- Correspondence: 0; 1983-1990 (Box-folder 004-002)
- Correspondence: University of Virginia President Robert M. O'Neil; 1985-1989 (Box-folder 004-003)
  Includes correspondence concerning the dedication of the new hospital.
- Correspondence: Pa-Pe; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 004-004)
  Includes correspondence concerning People to People International.
- Correspondence: Pf-Pz; 1982-1990 (Box-folder 004-005)
  Includes correspondence with Hiram C. Polk.
- Correspondence: R; 1982-1989 (Box-folder 004-006)
  Includes correspondence with Mark M. Ravitch, Jonathan E. Rhoads and Charles S. Robb
- Correspondence: S; 1951-1989 (Box-folder 004-007)
  Includes correspondence with Robert S. Sparkman and H. William Scott.
- Correspondence: V-W; 1968-1981 (Box-folder 004-008)
  Includes correspondence with Richard L. Varco
- Albemarle County Medical Society; 1945-1974 (Box-folder 005-001)
  Includes 1945 Constitution and By-laws of the Albemarle County Medical Society, 1974 proposed revised By-laws, a 1958 document investigating the feasibility of a program to make every doctor's office a cancer detection center, and a 1961 document concerning civil Defense emergency medical Services.
- American Board of Surgery; 1968-1972 (Box-folder 005-002)
  Most documents concern dual appointments (internship and junior assistant residency positions simultaneously) and graduate education in surgery more generally. Also included is a 1968 and 1972 "Guide book for Residency Programs in General Surgery."
- American College of Surgeons; 1976-1977 (Box-folder 005-003)
  Includes congratulatory letters to Muller on his election as Chairman of the American College of Surgeons Board of Regents and Muller's thank you letters in response.
- American College of Surgeons; 1977-1978 (Box-folder 005-004)
  Includes letters related to Muller's presentation as the Gibbon lecturer at the American College of Surgeons as well as the text of his lecture.
- American College of Surgeons; 1990-1992 (Box-folder 005-005)
  Includes reports related to Medicare.
- American Surgical Association; 1974-1975 (Box-folder 005-006)
  This is the time period when Dr. Muller was president of the ASA.
- Association for Academic Surgery; 1966-1980 (Box-folder 005-007)
- Association of American Medical Colleges; 1976 (Box-folder 005-008)
- Blalock lectureship; 1967-1986 (Box-folder 005-009)
  Includes a 25 page letter and drafts written to Dr. Mark Ravitch in which Muller recalls his memories of Dr. Alfred Blalock. Other items are programs for the Alfred Blalock Lectureship and a program from the Blalock Heritage in American Surgery with signatures of the speakers (Boone Powell, B. F. Bennett, Robert S. Sparkman, Abner V. McCall, W. Dewey Presley, David C. Sabiston, Mark M. Ravitch, C. Rollins Hanlon, Frank C. Spencer, William H. Muller, James V. Maloney, Denton A. Cooley, H. William Scott, G. Rainey Williams, J. Alex Haller, Henry T. Bahnson, and William P. Longmire) and spouses.
- Bohemian Club; 1976 (Box-folder 005-010)
  Bohemian Club gathers for a summer encampment at the Bohemian Grove in Monte Rio, California.
- Buffalo, New York talk; 1962, includes photo (Box-folder 005-011)
  Muller's talk was for the 13th Annual Surgical Residents' Reunion.
- Greenbrier Clinic Advisory Council, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia; 1960-1988 (Box-folder 005-012)
- Greenville County Medical Society, Greenville, S.C. talk; 1963-1964 (Box-folder 005-013)
- Halsted Society; 1958-1959 (Box-folder 006-001)
  Includes a copy of Muller's Halsted Society application and a photo of the 1959 meeting participants which did not include Muller as he was just elected at that time.
- Halsted Society; 1960-1961 (Box-folder 006-002)
  Photo of the 1960 meeting includes Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1962-1963 (Box-folder 006-003)
  Photo of the 1962 meeting does not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1964-1965 (Box-folder 006-004)
  Photo of the 1964 meeting does not include Muller. Photo of the 1965 meeting includes Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1966-1967 (Box-folder 006-005)
  Photos of the February 1967 and September 1967 meetings includes Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1968-1969 (Box-folder 006-006)
  Includes "The Founding and First Meeting of the Halsted Society" by Lawrence R. Wharton, Written for the members of the Halsted Society, and filed with its Archives 1968.
- Halsted Society; 1970-1971 (Box-folder 006-007)
  Photos of the 1970 and 1971 meetings do not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1972-1973 (Box-folder 006-008)
  Photos of the 1972 and 1973 meetings do not include Muller. Includes letters from Alfred Blalock's residents, members of the Old Hands Club, upon the occasion of the dedication of the Alfred Blalock Library at the Texas Heart Institute.
- Halsted Society; 1974-1975 (Box-folder 006-009)
  Includes a reprint of "The Halsted Society, 1924-1974" by Peter D. Olch and Halsted's bibliography. Photo of the 1974 meeting includes Muller. Photo of the 1975 meeting does not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1976-1977 (Box-folder 006-010)
  Photo of the 1976 meeting includes Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1978-1979 (Box-folder 007-001)
  Photos of the 1977 and 1979 meetings do not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1980-1981 (Box-folder 007-002)
  Photo of the 1981 meeting does not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1982-1983 (Box-folder 007-003)
  Photo of the 1983 meeting does not include Muller.
- Halsted Society; 1985-1986 (Box-folder 007-004)
- Henry Ford Hospital International Symposium on Cardiac Surgery; 1975 (Box-folder 007-005)
- International Federation of Surgical Colleges; 1980 (Box-folder 007-006)
  Includes a certificate for William H. Muller stating he is enrolled as an Associate in The International Federation of Surgical Colleges.
- International Society for Cardiovascular Surgery / Society for Vascular Surgery; 1983-1988 (Box-folder 007-007)
- International Society of Surgery / Societe Internationale de Chirurgie; 1959-1976 (Box-folder 007-008)
- Kentucky Surgical Society; 1983 (Box-folder 007-009)
  Muller is made an honorary member in the Society due to being a previous guest and speaker in 1955.
- Medical Society of Virginia; 1954-1963 (Box-folder 007-010)
  Included is a letter welcoming Muller as a member as well as meeting programs.
- Medical Society of Virginia; 1965-1983 (Box-folder 007-011)
  Included are meeting programs.
- Medical University of South Carolina; 1974 (Box-folder 007-012)
  Muller is invited to receive the Fourth Frederick E. Kredel Honorary Professorship of the Medical University of South Carolina and is asked to speak.
- National Joint Practice Commission, National Commission for the Study of Nursing and Nursing Education; 1971-1974 (Box-folder 008-001)
  Includes a certificate of recognition for Muller's participation in and contribution to the National Joint Practice Commission.
- Northwestern University; 1974-1981 (Box-folder 008-002)
  Includes correspondence related to Muller's participation on the External Review of Northwestern University's Department of Surgery as well as the report. Additional correspondence relates to Muller being a Visiting Professor and Guest Speaker at the annual meeting of the Department of Surgery at Northwestern.
- President's Panel on Heart Disease, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; 1972 (Box-folder 008-003)
- Rudolph Matas lectureship, Tulane University; 1964 (Box-folder 008-004)
- Society of Surgical Chairman; 1966-1976 (Box-folder 008-005)
  Includes a copy of the Constitution.
- Society of University Surgeons; 1958-1962 (Box-folder 008-006)
  Includes a group photo with Muller.
- Society of University Surgeons; 1963 (Box-folder 008-007)
- Society of University Surgeons - Special Committees; 1963-1964 (Box-folder 008-008)
  Includes correspondence for the following committees: Academic Placement, American Board of Surgery representatives, Fountain Report and NIH Grants Manual, International Responsibility, National Research Council, National Society for Research, and Surgical Education.
- Society of University Surgeons; 1964 (Box-folder 008-009)
- Society of University Surgeons; 1966 (Box-folder 008-010)
- Society of University Surgeons; 1967-1968 (Box-folder 008-011)
- Society of University Surgeons; 1975-1976 (Box-folder 008-012)
- Society of University Surgeons; 1980-1989 (Box-folder 008-013)
- Society of University Surgeons; 1985-1989 (Box-folder 009-001)
  Correspondence is related to support for membership in the Society of University Surgeons for Raymond F. Morgan.
- Southern Society for Clinical Research; 1955-1967 (Box-folder 009-002)
  Includes document that gives a brief history, constitution and bylaws, officers and living members from 1947-1967 for the Society.
- Southern Surgical Association; 1974-1980 (Box-folder 009-003)
  Includes letters congratulating Muller on his election as President of the Southern Surgical Association as well as Muller's replies.
- University of Virginia Clinical Appointments to the Medical Policy Committee; 1983-1991 (Box-folder 009-004)
  Lists names of appointees and dates of the appointments.
- University of Virginia Continuing Medical Education Committee; 1987-1990 (Box-folder 009-005)
  Includes reports and also letters from Norman Knorr, Daniel Mohler, Leslie Rudolf, Muller, John A. Owen and others.
- University of Virginia. Department of Surgery Attending Staff Lists and letters related to staffing; 1954-1989 (Box-folder 009-006)
- University of Virginia. Department of Surgery House Staff; 1954-1981 (Box-folder 009-007)
- University of Virginia Health Services Foundation: Comments; 1988 (Box-folder 009-008)
  Muller's comments describe the background for the need for the Health Services Foundation and its start. He mentions the contributions of Jay Gillenwater, Leigh Middleditch, Hovey Dabney, Ray Bell, Jean Printz, and Billy Williams.
- University of Virginia. Instructions for Appointments of Staff to Hospital; 1971-1981 (Box-folder 009-009)
  Includes Employee benefits outline
- Vanderbilt University - Barney Brooks Lecturer; 1975-1976 (Box-folder 009-010)
- Clippings concerning people and topics of interest to Dr. Muller; 1971-1982, newspaper clippings, journal clippings (Box-folder 009-011)
  Includes a number of clippings about J. Shelton Horsley
- unidentified people at a festive occasion; n.d., photos (Box-folder 009-012)
- William H. Muller, Jr.; n.d., photo 8x10 B&W (Box-folder 009-013)
- Hildwin Muller, William H. Muller, Jr., ? and Billy Old; n.d., photos (Box-folder 009-014)
- Dr. and Mrs. C. Bruce Morton and Dr. and Mrs. E. Cato Drash at the men's retirement; 1970, photos (Box-folder 009-015)
  Also included are pictures of the UVa Department of Surgery including Drs. Drash, Muller, Morton, Wangensteen, Harry Archer, Sandusky, Gaylord Williams, Gardner Smith, Arthur Smith, Nolan, Minor, Horsley, Wilhelm, and Schrum. Absent were Rudolf and Alrich.
- William H. Muller, Jr. and Hildwin Muller; 1988, n.d., passport photos and negatives (Box-folder 009-016)
- William H. Muller, Jr. and identified person in front of Muller Surgical Society board; April 1989, photo (Box-folder 009-017)
- Unidentified people at a festive occasion; January 17, 2004, photos (Box-folder 009-018)
- William H. Muller, Jr., Hildwin Muller, R. Scott Jones, Mrs. Jones (?); May 22, 2005, photos (Box-folder 009-019)
- miscellaneous photos; 2007, photos (Box-folder 009-020)
  The photos came from a folder marked 2007, but some individual photos are marked with different dates. Included are photos of Muller, R. Scott Jones, Stephen H. Watts, William H. Goodwin, and Edwin P. Lehman in their academic gowns; C. Bruce Morton; the first hospital pavilion, and hospital construction.
- Surgery Department University of Virginia Medical Center Scrapbook; 1967-1972, photos, newspaper and article clippings (Box-folder 009-021)
  Includes articles about surgical transplants, photos of Surgery Department Attendings and House Staff 1967-68 and 1969-70
- Highlights of the Consultants' Report on the Master Plan, press briefing 1980 November 6, 2 TD (Box-folder 010-001a)
  The consultants, E.D. Rosenfeld Associates Inc. and Baskervill & Son, recommend rebuilding the Medical Center on the Blue Ridge Hospital site.
- Memorandum from Jules I. Levine to W. H. Muller; 1981 April 24, 2 TD, ANS (Box-folder 010-001b)
  Medical Center and University Planning: Observations and Recommendations. Levine is concerned about the excessive workload placed upon the Department of Physical Plant and the Health Affairs Office due to the large number of minor and major renovations which are all expected to be created in a time frame that is not possible given the various entities involved.
- Executive Summary from Master Plan Update, 1981; 1981, November 19, 1 TD (Box-folder 010-002)
  Prepared by Maurice W. Perreault and Associates, Inc.
- Commonwealth of Virginia Capital Ourlay Request, Biennium 1984-86; 1982 December 7, 1 TDS, copy (Box-folder 010-003)
  Relates to the Replacement Hospital and site preparation; total cost of the project is estimated to be $128,166,000.
- Inside UVA: "Replacement hospital planners chosen"; 1983 January 1, 1 D (Box-folder 010-004)
- The Cavalier Daily: "Mounting unpaid bills threaten hospital's financial well-being"; 1983 January 21, newspaper clipping (Box-folder 010-005)
  Almost $8.5 million in bad debts and free service were incurred from August to November 1982.
- The Cavalier Daily: "Hereford will try to recoup state funds"; 1983 January 24, newspaper clipping (Box-folder 010-006)
  Gov. Robb proposed $55 millsion in state budget cuts to higher education.
- The Daily Progress: "UVa's Frank Hereford: A Personal Perspective"; 1983 February 27, newspaper clipping (Box-folder 010-007)
  Interview with Hereford
- The Daily Progress: "UVa's Ailing Hospital Plan"; 1983 March 27, newspaper clipping (Box-folder 010-008)
- The Cavalier Daily: "University uncovers its capital outlay proposals";1983 April 7, newspaper clipping (Box-folder 010-009)
- The Draw Sheet: "Building a replacement hospital"; 1983 September, 1 D (Box-folder 010-010)
- The Cavalier Daily: "State OKs 445-bed replacement hospital; 1984 march 5, newspaper (Box-folder 010-011)
- Inside UVA: "New hospital finance director appointed; 1984 May 1, 1 D (Box-folder 010-012)
- A special supplement to Inside UVa: "New Hospital Construction to Begin with November 7 Ground Breaking Event"; 1984 November 1, 1 D (Box-folder 010-013)
- The Draw Sheet: Groundbreaking set for new hospital and Inside UVa supplement: New Hospital Construction to Begin; 1984 November, 2 D (Box-folder 010-014a)